טוב, tov, we are back to being caught up, or more or
less. Today's דף daf is דף ו׳. daf vav. We pick up
on עמוד ב׳, amud bet, two dots, about ten lines from the
bottom, ומת חולצת. umet choletzet. So now we're dealing with an interesting
application about the case of יבום yibum for those who fondly remember
learning מסכת יבמות. Maseches Yevamos. So
basically this woman, now she was warned and she was went into
a seclusion with the appropriate witnesses at each stage, so now she's
a סוטה. Sotah.
And the הלכה halacha of סוטה Sotah is that she's a ספק
safek but she's treated as a ודאי, vaday, meaning we don't know
what her status is, but it's going to be clarified by the
ritual when she's brought to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But until
that status is clarified, she's treated as a ודאי vaday because the
language of the תורה Torah is ונטמאה, v'nitma'ah, right? ונסתרה והיא נטמאה.
v'nistarah v'hi nitma'ah.
So and then it says והיא לא נטמאה, v'hi lo nitma'ah, but
anyway, but it sort of just declares her as טמאה tmeiah once
these based on the well, according to the פשט הפסוקים peshat hapesukim
based on the suspicions, but according to the way חז״ל Chazal read
it based on this procedure or based on the evidence that we
have so far. So therefore the result of that status of that
ספק safek treated as ודאי vaday is that she's forbidden to have
sex with her husband, husband's forbidden to have sex with her, and
if she's married to a כהן kohen she can't eat תרומה. terumah.
And we're going to learn that later because it says ונטמאה v'nitma'ah
multiple times that somehow it has challenged, you know, the the status
of the marriage, that the marriage, I mean if you're not having
sex, you know, but the point is it's not just a technical
prohibition, there's some type of a there's some type of way in
which those bonds have been weakened or or you know somehow defiled.
So therefore she also cannot eat תרומה terumah if she's married to
a כהן. kohen. And then the משנה Mishnah says that if the
guy dies before they've had a chance to clarify her status, the
brother if they have no kids cannot do יבום. yibum. Now if
you just take a second and think about that because יבום yibum
is an act of sex, right, and it would mean beginning a
sexual relationship with this woman, but he's taking his brother's place and
the brother at this stage was forbidden to have sex with this
woman. So that's why it says he can't do יבום. yibum. On
the other hand she's not there's this element of doubt here whether
she really did commit adultery, so he still has to do חליצה.
chalitzah.
What about if the guy she was warned against being in secluded
with was the brother? Then there'd be יבום. yibum.
Okay, אסור לבעל ואסור לבועל. assur l'ba'al v'assur l'bo'el.
So alright, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמאי,
amay, ומת חולצת, v'met choletzet,
ואמאי v'amay says the גמרא Gemara תתיבם נמי יבומי. tityabem nami yibumei.
Let's first establish how we know he can't do יבום. yibum. So
אמר רב יוסף אמר קרא amar Rav Yosef amar kra ויצאה מביתו
והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר. v'yatz'ah mibeito v'halchah v'haytah l'ish acher.
She shall leave his house and go to be with another man.
This is a man who divorces a woman and in the פסוקים,
pesukim, right, כי מצא בה ערות דבר, ki matza bah ervat davar,
she's divorced because of some act of nakedness, meaning some sense of
sexual violation. So what we're going to assume is that that includes
a woman who is discovered to be not only committed adultery but
suspected of it, a woman who's a סוטה. Sotah. Now again the
פסוקים pesukim is that he divorced her, but we're reading the פסוקים
pesukim that once it's מצא בה ערות דבר, matza bah ervat davar,
then however she winds up leaving her first husband, whether he divorces
her or he dies, the next stage is והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר.
v'halchah v'haytah l'ish acher. And the דרשה drasha is איש אחר ולא
יבם, ish acher v'lo yavam, that she can only go to another
man but she's forbidden to the brother-in-law. So again a very particular
read of the פסוקים. pesukim. We're reading it specifically that it's a
case of a סוטה, Sotah, not a definite adultery or anything else,
and that not that she was divorced but under whatever circumstances she
is no longer with her first husband, the next guy she marries
has to be somebody completely different, cannot be somebody who's essentially a
continuation of her first husband.
Yes. But the whole basis of יבום yibum is that the first
husband dies and then there's יבום yibum
as opposed to divorce you mean? Yeah. So there's no question that
it's not פשט peshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. רש״י Rashi is saying
that this דרשה drasha is reading it like okay that it's ויצאה
מביתו, v'yatz'ah mibeito, he writes her גט, get, or but really however
she winds up leaving him, והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר, v'halchah v'haytah l'ish
acher, the next stage has to be a completely different man.
And in this case there's just a מצוה mitzvah for her to
be with
this other man in the case of יבום. yibum. Right, well that's
what the גמרא Gemara is going to get to, but anyway, but
yeah it's clearly a very particular, narrow, you know, and strange read
of the פסוק. pasuk.
But at this moment in the דרשה drasha it's saying that you
can never do יבום yibum in a case of a divorce that
was motivated by...
well you never do יבום yibum in a divorce, right. The strange
read is that we're ignoring the divorce stage of the narrative of
the פסוקים pesukim and saying מצא בה ערות דבר matza bah ervat
davar and then she always has to go to somebody completely different,
never to a יבם.
yavam. But then if you accept that read, yes,
but
there's still it shouldn't be superseded by the מצוה mitzvah of death
and and the requirement for יבום. yibum.
Right, well that's what we're learning from these פסוקים pesukim that that's
excluded. Right. Clearly as the גמרא Gemara is going to say there's
a lot of אמר אביי אלא מעתה חליצה נמי לא תיבעי. Amar
Abaye ella me'ata chalitzah nami lo tiba'i. So if you're
saying that it's excluded from יבום yibbum based on this פסוק, pasuk,
so then you shouldn't need חליצה, chalitzah, there should be no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibbum at all. אמר ליה אילו איתיה לבעל מי
לא בעי גט. Amar leh ilu itei leva'al mi lo ba'ei get.
Look, if the husband was around, even though she now is a
סוטה, sotah, you would still need to sever that bond through a
גט. get. השתא נמי תיבעי חליצה. Hash'ta nami tiba'i chalitzah. So here
too, the relationship, you know, the connection of the husband, what we
call the זיקה, zika, transfers to the brother. So, and that bond
has not been severed, even if she committed adultery, it needs to
be formally severed. So the husband would have to sever with a
גט, get, he'll have to sever with חליצה. chalitzah. So even if
יבום yibbum is not an option, you still need to sever the
bond with חליצה. chalitzah. Now תוספות Tosafot points out that the logic
here is a bit of a problem, because there are many situations
in which the brother does not do יבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitzah,
but if the husband was alive, he would still need a גט.
get. Right, let's say she was an ערווה ervah to the brother,
right? Let's say it was a case about a woman who was
an אילונית, ailonit, not able to have kids. Let's say even if
it was a woman who had definitely committed adultery. In all those
cases, the husband, if he was alive, would need to give her
a גט. get. The bond doesn't sever automatically, but nevertheless, once she's
fundamentally excluded from the מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, there's no need
for חליצה. chalitzah. All right, so it's not, you know, it doesn't
really work, that argument. So תוספות Tosafot in the end basically winds
up saying what the גמרא Gemara's going to say. That's not really
based on the פסוק pasuk and this argument that we're shaping because
again, if so, how would you know that she wouldn't be fully
excluded and not even חליצה? chalitzah? And it's really just going to
be based on the fact that if the husband can't be having
sex with her, then how does the brother, whose relationship is a
continuation of the husband's relationship, wind up basically having sex with her?
That's really what the argument is. So all the various questions everybody
is asking, you know, תוספות Tosafot sort of concedes like, bottom line
is, it's not really these דרשות. drashot. Yes, Dov.
Is this line here, אילו איתיה לבעל מי לא בעי
גט,
ilu itei leva'al mi lo
ba'ei get, at what point in the סוטה sotah process would he
have to issue her a גט? get?
So if she is definitely... well, if she's definitely...
No,
no, no, he never has to issue her a גט, get, she
might turn out to be okay, right? So if it turns out
that she's guilty, then he has to issue her a גט, get,
or if she refuses to drink, if she, or if she admits
her guilt, or any type of a thing where we don't, where
she currently has a status of being forbidden because of the doubt,
and either that status is confirmed or it's never going to be
resolved.
Okay, but as long as she's drinking, she
doesn't need a גט, get, she'll just die, if it works, so
to speak, she's dead.
According to the פסוקים, pesukim, the פסוקים pesukim don't make it sound
like she dies, but according to חז"ל, Chazal, who understand that she
dies as a result of it, then yes, then you don't need
a גט, get, you'll be, you know, because she'll be dead. Right.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, but it never ends
by itself; you always need a גט. get. All right, so that's
the דרשה, drasha, but again, there's a problem with that logic, because
if it really is excluded from יבום, yibbum, then yeah, even if
the husband needs a גט, get, she should not need חליצה. chalitzah.
But we'll see, the גמרא Gemara's going to continue to make clear
what sort of its logic is. And it says like this, איכא
דאמרי, ika de'amri, and others say, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef,
רחמנא אמר, Rachamana amar, ויצאה מביתו והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר, veyatza mibeito
vehalcha vehayetah le'ish acher, that after this case of מצא בה ערות
דבר, matza bah ervat davar, she goes to another man. אחרי דסני
לה, acharei desani lah, to another. Why? דלא תיסתרי לביתו. dela tistari
leveito. The point is, this guy has a responsibility of divorcing her
so she should not, you know, destroy the house, like she's now
a woman who's, you know, suspected of adultery, or... and we learned
before how what the גמרא Gemara particularly emphasizes the women, anyway,
when there's cheating going on in the marriage, it destroys the household.
So that's why he divorced her. ואת אמרת תתיבם נמי יבומי? ve'at
amrat tityabem nami yibumi? So you want this guy now to go
ahead and do יבום? yibbum? After, you know, the whole point was
to... the whole point... no, but it's בתמיהא. bitmiha. The whole point
was to get rid of this woman because she's a danger to
the marriage. Now there's... now the גמרא Gemara's going to say, well
then everybody else should be forbidden to marry her also, if she's
perceived of as such a danger. So let's take a look at
the next line. אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, אלא מעתה, ella
me'ata, לאחר לא תינסי, le'acher lo tinasei, דלא תיסתרי לביתו. dela tistari
leveito. So any woman who is divorced or, you know, in this
case of יבום, yibbum, widowed after being suspected of having committed adultery,
it should be forbidden for anybody to marry her. You know, and
again, the point is that she's only suspected,
but nevertheless, if that's what you're saying, that we're going to assume
or whatever, be concerned that maybe she did it, and that's why
the guy can't do יבום, yibbum, then nobody should be allowed to
marry her. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה, amar leh, he
said back to him, מי קא רמינא לה עליה בעל כרחיה? mi
ka ramina lah aleih be'al korchei? No, everybody else doesn't... isn't required...
isn't obligated to marry her. So you know, it's like buyer beware,
you know? You know the circumstances, you make your choice. choice, okay?
But at least that's your choice. All right, whereas here how could
it be that the תורה Torah would obligate the brother to marry
this woman after you know these problematic circumstances? All right, so that's
sort of the argument. Now again, so but how do you know
you get to this middle stage where okay, you don't do יבום
yibum but you do חליצה? chalitzah? But maybe that's the point, like
we're not saying she's completely excluded. And again, it's really she's not
a ודאי vaday סוטה soteh or she definitely committed adultery. It's only
a doubt, but that doubt should be enough of an obstacle, you
know, to do יבום yibum even though because it's not definite, there
still is required a חליצה. chalitzah. Yes.
Every once in a while, I'm reminded of Chava Miss Rivka because
no doubt she would point out that just because she's suspected or
even committed adultery doesn't mean it was all on her. Right. Sure,
she's, if it was so, she was the one who committed the
act. But the relationship between them and what the husband did, you
know.
Well, I really first of all do appreciate those
comments, well, I, boy, you know, shouldn't be... or he's going to
destroy a house.
Well, that's true also. Yesterday, yesterday we focused on the adulterer, the
male, the man who's the adulterer and his responsibility about that. But
I really appreciate those comments, which is you know even if until
now what I've really been saying is she's only been suspected and
maybe he's suspecting her because he's jealous and it hasn't really happened,
but I think Dov also makes an excellent point, like you know
even if she actually did it, what's going on in the relationship
that she you know there are times when you know there is
about who's at fault to blame in these types of circumstances is
not at all clear. So I really do appreciate that.
And yes, and here, okay so whoever's fault it was, let's separate
these two families, right?
Yeah, but not these two families. Anyway, right.
But even if it was his fault, then you know whatever, okay.
Like why does that mean the brother will be the same, will
be different than the third party altogether?
Well because you know people's allegiances are often with their...
okay, maybe, and actually we're going to see about that in a
minute. But here at this stage what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is that given the suspicion and the question, whatever, there's no way
you can mandate that this other man, people can choose to and
another man can choose to, but you can't mandate that this brother
would actually now have to go ahead and marry her once these
questions have been raised. But because it's not definite and all those
things and it's only a doubt, we can't require it, but there
still needs to be a חליצה chalitzah that needs to be done.
Now there's a very nice little תוספות Tosafot at the bottom of
ה עמוד ב. Hey Amud Bet. וליסתור לביתו ואת אמרת תתייבם נמי
ייבומי. ulistore l'beyteh, v'at amrat tityabem nami yibumei. The תוספות Tosafot points
out the phrase וליסתור לביתו, ulistore l'beyteh, to destroy the house. Where's
that phrase coming from?
So תוספות Tosafot says very nicely, רבינו חננאל הטעים דבריו. Rabbeinu Chananel
hit-im devarav. It's very
nice. רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel explained what אביי Abaye was saying. הטעים
דבריו, hit-im devarav, like he gave a little טעם ta'am to you
know he helped explain what אביי Abaye meant. And here's what he
said, but I just love that phrase הטעים דבריו. hit-im devarav.
Like he... what?
He sweetened, right, what אביי Abaye was saying. ופירש ורחמנא אמר אשר
לא יבנה לבנות ולא לסתור, Upirash v'rachmana amar asher lo yivneh, livnot
v'lo listor, right? Where did this phrase come ליסתור לביתו, listore l'beyteh,
destroy the house? It is the exact inverse of אשר לא יבנה
את בית אחיו asher lo yivneh et beit achiv that
the obligation of the יבם yavam is to build the house. So
this woman who's suspected, it's like you know being a home-wrecker, right?
That would be the ליסתור לביתו, listore l'beyteh, so how could that
be in the מצוה mitzvah of building the house? All right, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. But again, it's only a suspicion
and therefore חליצה chalitzah still needed. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika d'amrei, and some
say, אמר רב יוסף הכתוב קראו אחר, Amar Rav Yosef hakasuv kara
acher, when it says marry another man, כשאין בן זוגו של ראשון,
k'she-ein bein zugo shel rishon, he is not a appropriate like equal
of the first guy. Like what does that mean? שזה הוציא רשעה
מביתו, she-zeh hotzi rishah mibeito, the first guy did the right thing,
he got rid of this wicked woman. Again, notice how...
from a regular divorce?
No, when it's because of מצא בה ערות דבר. matza bah ervat
davar. So we're all assuming that we're dealing, the context is סוטה,
sotah, a woman who's suspected. And even though, again, once again notice
that she's labeled as a רשעה. rishah.
But how is he מוציא? motzi?
He divorced her. What do you mean?
I'm sorry, I asked what I asked you, if we're talking about...
but not a regular divorce that's a result of כי מצא בה
ערות
דבר.
ki matza bah
ervat davar. Okay. So a woman is suspected of being a סוטה
sotah and he basically divorced her, but again just labeling her as
a רשעה rishah just because of the suspicion. וזה, Ve-zeh, and the
guy who now marries this woman who was מצא בה ערות דבר
matza bah ervat davar and divorced, הכניס ואיש אחר, hichnis v'ish acher,
he's like of a different... he's of a different category because he
was prepared to marry such a woman. הכניס רשעה לתוך ביתו. Hichnis
rishah l'toch beito. So that's in a normal case where we're dealing
with divorce, but again it's a מצא בה ערות דבר. matza bah
ervat davar. The point being that somebody who chooses to marry this
woman is considered to be like not acting properly. He's you know
he's אחר, acher, he's not in the same מדריגה madregah as the
guy who understood... who divorced her. ואת אמרת תתייבם נמי ייבומי? V'at
amrat tityabem nami yibumei? So if that's how we look at the
guy who married her, you're going to say that the תורה Torah
is now going to mandate that a man's going to marry this
woman after if she's left widowed from... this guy after she's suspected?
So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said אלא
מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's true that the תורה Torah can never
mandate it, right, because how could the תורה Torah mandate marrying this
woman who's suspected of having committed adultery? So I'll give you a
case where the תורה Torah will mandate it. How will that be?
ניסת לאחר, nisas l'acher, let's say she's suspected of committing adultery, she
goes ahead and is widowed or divorced from guy number one, marries
guy number two, has a completely happy marriage with guy number two,
okay, ומת, umais, and then guy number two dies, בלא בנים, belo
banim, and now guy number two's brothers are obligated to do יבום
yibbum with this woman who was suspected of having committed adultery while
she was married to guy number one. So לא תתייבם? lo tisyabem?
So you telling me that she shouldn't do, that the brother shouldn't
do יבום? yibbum? דקרא קרי ליה אחר גביה, d'kra kari lei acher
gabei, so אחר, acher, that the פסוק pasuk calls this guy an
אחר, acher, that he was like on a lower level that he
was willing to marry her and that really the תורה Torah would
never want to mandate anybody should marry the woman suspected of adultery?
So גמרא Gemara says no, גבי דהאי מי בא בשם טוב הוא
קאי. gabi d'hai mi b'shem tov hu ka-i. So now here is
like you're... but the second guy, she actually had a good reputation.
So maybe she did תשובה, teshuva, maybe it shows that she never
committed adultery, so the way we look at it...
maybe the problem was with the first guy?
Maybe the problem was with the first guy, so now in this
context we look at her differently, yes, and that's
now we're focusing on the woman, right? The guy who married her,
how did he know that it was gonna work?
He didn't! So number two who married her shouldn't have married her,
shouldn't have married her, right? We're not saying number two should've married
her. But by the time number two dies, when now we come
to the question of יבום, yibbum, now we look at her relationship
with number two. We're prepared to reassess.
But you're sort of skipping, or eliding the question. The question is:
should the תורה Torah be prescribing יבום yibbum for a person, for
the wife of a man who's not worthy?
No, no, no, the point was, since
the תורה Torah calls the second guy אחר, acher, it shows
that he made a wrong decision marrying such a woman. So that
shows us that it's wrong to marry such a woman. So therefore
the תורה Torah would never mandate יבום yibbum with such a woman.
Okay, so now it's saying but after, after guy number two did
the wrong thing and married her and now they've been having a
happy marriage and she has not been suspected of adultery with guy
number two, it shows us now that actually she might not be
such a bad woman.
It's not so... it's not so simple though, since it's...
and you're saying exactly the same thing
as before, it's more of a reflection on the first husband, you
could say.
Maybe
she was suspected, but she did תשובה teshuva or something.
No, not he, she, she! Not her...
the
second guy had nothing to do with it, the second guy had
nothing to do with it.
What do we call the second guy an אחר acher is only
a way to get to the fact that she is a problem.
We don't care about the second guy having done something wrong, it
only reflects the fact that she's a problem and she should not
be a woman that people should be marrying. That's the way the
גמרא Gemara is making the argument.
The whole point...
what? If you, the אחר, acher, the second guy, the first guy
knew what to do with such a woman, he divorced her. The
second guy was too focused on his own desire or attraction or
whatever and he is not of the same מדריגה madrega as the
first guy. That's a bad choice to marry such a woman, that's
the way it's reading it. So it reflects...
that's the point he's making, that the word אחר acher intrinsically has
a negative connotation.
That's the way... right.
Not because
of the guy, because of the woman, the סוטה. Sota.
No, because of the woman.
All right, I think we should move on.
Let's move on. We're only talking about the man to reflect the
status of the woman. All right, we're moving on. I can't spend
more time on this.
Yeah, I also have not managed, what happened?
I know, I'm not getting why everybody's so confused but we'll talk
about it more after class. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: רבא אמר קל וחומר, Rava amar kal vachomer, אם נאסרה במותר
לה אסורה באסור לה לא כל שכן. im ne'esra b'muttar lah asura
b'assur lah lo kol sheken. Look, רבא Rava says
the guy she was מותר muttar to, her husband, this act of
now that she became a סוטה Sota and suspected of adultery made
her forbidden to her husband. So this, so how now if this
thing makes her now forbidden to the person she's permissible to, that
she's married to, the brother of the guy who while she's, while
her husband is still alive is עריות arayos to her, is forbidden
to her, a, she's a married woman, and b, it's her husband's
brother. So how much more so should this act now sort of
make, you know, make her forbidden to the brother? So if being
a סוטה Sota strong enough to make her forbidden to her husband,
certainly it should make her forbidden to the brother. Now again, it's
a questionable argument because why don't we say that it should make
her forbidden to everyone? Forbidden to everyone! All right, but the brother,
but the point here is there's already a problem with her marrying
the brother, that it's an עריות. arayos. So and therefore if there's
another monkey wrench thrown in there, something else problematic, there's no way
we're going to מתיר mattir that relationship with the brother.
All right, okay. doesn't really matter. ומת, u-met, ויש לו אח כהן
הדיוט, ve-yesh lo ach kohen hedyot, and he dies and he has
a brother who is a normal כהן. kohen. ולא תתייבם, ve-lo tityabbem,
so this brother can't do ייבום. yibbum. Why? אי נאסרה במותר לה,
ee ne'esrah be-muttar lah, because this widow was forbidden to her husband,
which was because the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, widow's only forbidden to
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, באסורה לה לא כל שכן, ba-asurah lah
lo kol sheken, how much more so should she be now forbidden
to the husband's brother. Which is not true because she is only
an אלמנה. almanah. So the גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, that's not a good comparison. הא אסירה וקיימא. ha asirah
ve-kaima.
So first of all, what do you mean she became forbidden? She
didn't become forbidden to her husband. As an אלמנה, almanah, she was
always forbidden to her husband as the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So
מותר לה, muttar lah, so it's not she's not forbidden to a
man who was permissible to her, אסורה לה, asurah lah, he was
always forbidden to her. So that's not a relevant example. It's not
like something now affected her status that somehow you know challenged the
marriage and got in the way of the marriage which now also
logically also have an impact on the יבם. yavam. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אלא, ella,
okay here's the example. אשת כהן שנאנסה. Eshet kohen she-ne'ensah. A woman
is married to a כהן kohen and she was raped. ומת u-met
and then the brother died. ויש לו אח חלל. ve-yesh lo ach
challal. So now that act of rape made her forbidden to her
husband.
But the brother,
he has actually a brother who is a חלל. challal. How could
that be if it only has to be a father's brother for
ייבום? yibbum? That the father then married another woman who was let's
say a גרושה gerushah and therefore the child which would be a
חלל challal and right, it's
an אב av and both
are both from father now. Exactly. So in this case would you
say who is permissible to marry such a woman? A woman who
you know so would you say לא תתייבם? lo tisyabbem? He shouldn't
do ייבום. yibbum. Why? Here's your logic. אי נאסרה במותר לה. ee
ne'esrah be-muttar lah. This act of rape made her forbidden to her
husband who was permissible to her. באסורה לה לא כל שכן. ba-asurah
lah lo kol sheken. How much more so should it make
it forbidden to the man who was permissible to her, I say
permissible excuse me, how much more so should it make it forbidden
to the brother. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אונס בישראל מישרא
שרי. ones be-yisrael mishra sharei. Look, a case of rape by a
non-כהן kohen does not make a woman forbidden. וגבי דהאי ליכא איסורא.
ve-gabbi de-hai leika issura. And regarding the brother who is a חלל,
challal, he's basically a non-כהן. kohen. It's not a forbidden status at
all, meaning being a woman committing adultery would be if would be
just as a relevant of a problem if she was married to
her current husband as well as if she was married to the
brother, right? Because being adulterous is always a problem for in any
relationship. Okay, and therefore if it got if it affected her current
marriage to her husband she was permissible to, how much more so
should that be a status that carries over and remains a problem
to the case of ייבום, yibbum, to the brother, which is a
continuation of that and it's also problematic because of brother, how much
more so should that problematic status carry over? Whereas the case of
rape of being married to a כהן kohen doesn't isn't isn't relevant
to people that are not כהנים. kohanim. So obviously it shouldn't affect
her relationship with the brother if the brother is not a כהן.
kohen. חליצה. chalitzah.
So he could do ייבום. yibbum.
So one way or another way we basically have said by you
know and the logic really makes a lot of sense, if this
status makes sex forbidden with her husband, how can the תורה Torah
go ahead and mandate ייבום yibbum which is when you see the
brother basically as a continuation of the relationship of you know the
dead husband. Okay, but because it's only based on suspicion and not
definite knowledge, the חליצה chalitzah is still required.
Yeah. Why did the סוגיא sugya to סוגיא sugya doing here, why
did it bring the case of the כהן גדול kohen gadol and
the חלל? challal?
Because it wanted to sort of make a question the argument that
if she becomes forbidden to her husband how much more so should
she become forbidden to the husband's brother. So it says there's cases
where she's forbidden to the husband and not forbidden.
Ah, but wouldn't he have had to have divorced the wife once
she got raped?
Yeah, but it didn't happen, he didn't have a chance to. Oh
oh oh okay.
So is a
חלל challal considered a כהן? kohen? What? Is a חלל challal considered
No. So
if in this case, is he just marrying her or is he
doing ייבום? yibbum?
He would do ייבום. yibbum.
But then the idea of ייבום yibbum is to continue the name
of the brother. That's right.
I mean it's a little ironic. It's continuing the name but not
as but not as a כהן. kohen. It's a good point, it
is ironic. Okay, but if he divorced
her, then there's no ייבום yibbum obviously.
Right. Okay, so now let's now let's move on. ואלו אסורות מלאכול
בתרומה. ve-ellu assurot me-le'echol bi-trumah.
So since we said that in her suspected status she can't eat
תרומה, trumah, we're going to mention other cases that they can't eat
תרומה, trumah, which basically means we'll see that basically statuses that are
not going to get you know when can't get resolved through drinking
the סוטה Sotah waters or essentially these are cases that are not
don't have the option of getting resolved. So while she's still suspected
she can't eat תרומה trumah and there are cases and the only
way she'll get out of that essentially is if it gets resolved
through the סוטה Sotah process. So let's... Let's take a look. ואלו
אסורות מלאכול בתרומה *Ve'elu asurot milachol biterumah*, האומרת טמאה אני ha'omeret temei'a
ani, לך *Ha'omeret teme'ah ani lach*. Let's say she basically admits that
she had committed adultery. Okay? Then fine, ends right there. ושבאו עדים
edim שהיא טמאה teme'ah. *Veshavo eidim shehi teme'ah*
or let's say witnesses came and said that she had committed adultery.
Again, well, there wasn't התראה *hatzra'ah* or something, but whatever. Anyway, so
these are obvious, in a way it's funny, if as a suspected
woman she can't eat תרומה terumah? *terumah*, certainly in these cases where
she even admits to it, but the point is then it doesn't
even hold up the option, and then the whole process stops right
there. There's not going to be a
סוטה Sotah's *sotah* process. ואומרת איני שותה *Ve'omeret eini shotah* and if
she says I don't want, I refuse, I refuse to go through
the process, או שהבעל אינו רוצה להשקותה *O sheba'al eino rotzeh lehashkotah*,
or the husband refuses to go through the process. So in a
way all of these are really telling us, not just it's funny
that it phrases it as אסורות מלאכול בתרומה *asurot milachol biterumah*, what
all of these are telling us are these are scenarios where the
process... you'll never get to doing the process. What happens when you
don't have the option anymore of doing it? He refuses, she refuses,
she admits or whatever. Basically she gets divorced without a כתובה *ketubah*.
Okay? And in all of those cases... well actually if the husband
refuses she might actually get the כתובה *ketubah*. I don't remember, but
presumably she does because it's his fault. But anyway, all those cases
it's not going to get resolved, so she continues to remain forbidden
to be אוכלת בתרומה *ochelet biterumah*. ושבא בעלה בדרך *Veshavah ba'alah baderech*
or if the husband had sex with her on the way to
doing the whole process, so that if that happens, then he himself
has violated the restrictions of the סוטה Sotah *sotah*, and in those
cases you don't go through with the process of the water. Okay?
So in all those cases you're not going to go through the
process and therefore she is going to have to get divorced with
or without כתובה *ketubah* depending on whose fault it was and she's
going to remain forbidden because the situation will never get resolved.
What if he dies? Does she get the כתובה *ketubah* or not?
We'll see about that. From what I remember the answer is no,
but we'll see about that.
Why does he have to give a divorce to stay if they're
still married and he decides he really does want to keep her
as his wife?
Because once he created her status as a סוטה *sotah* by warning
her and her going into private, then that status doesn't get removed
until the situation gets clarified. So she remains forbidden to him. So
but you're right, I mean could there
be a
way of retroactively retracting, retracting your whole thing, right? So alright, let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. I mean in a
way it's ironic, the תורה Torah *Torah* makes it all based on
the husband's jealousy. So according to the תורה *Torah* once the husband
stops being jealous the whole thing falls apart. חז"ל *Chazal* that wanted
to take it out of that, just because a man is jealous
doesn't mean he gets to do all this to his wife and
wanted to make it something a little bit more objective
and juridical and put it under בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din*
and there's evidence and there's a basis of suspicion and so on,
but then that also takes his discretion away from him to a
certain degree.
Let's see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אמר רב Rav עמרם *Amar Rav
Amram* said רב עמרם *Rav Amram*, הא מילתא אמר לן רב ששת
Rav Sheshet. *ha milsa amar lan Rav Sheshet*, the following thing רב
ששת Rav Sheshet *Rav Sheshet* said to us, ואנהיר לה עינין ממתניתין
*ve'anhir lah einan mimatnisa*, and he lightened our eyes from the משנה
Mishnah. *mishna*, he brought light to our eyes, he showed us that
this חידוש chiddush? *chiddush* of his was really buried in the משנה
Mishnah *mishna*. So let's see what his חידוש *chiddush* was. סוטה שיש
לה עדים במדינת הים edim b'medinas hayam *Sotah sheyesh lah eidim bimdinat
hayam*. There's a woman suspected of adultery and there are witnesses somewhere
overseas, very very distant, that knows that she's committed adultery. אין המים
בודקין אותה *Ein hamayim bodkin osah*. So now they went and they
were not aware of those witnesses and they went through the whole
process and she was... the water didn't have its effect. So everybody's
now assuming she's innocent. So he says no, the reason the water
didn't have its effect is because there's actually concrete evidence. Okay? The
whole point of the ritual is when there's a doubt, but when
that... like when it can't be resolved objectively. But when there actually
is objective evidence, even if we don't know it, then the ritual
gets neutralized. Okay? Now of course you're going to say to yourself
so how do we ever know why she came out clean, right?
So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to get to that. Okay. So...
know how
common that really was.
Exactly, something...
wait wait wait, you need עדים eidim *eidim* for the סתירה stira,
*stirah*, right? For the two... you need עדים edim *eidim* for טומאה
*tumah*, right?
What do you mean? You
need... for it to go through the process, you need עדים *eidim*...
what do you mean? No, to go through the process you need
עדים *eidim* that she... that she was warned and that she went
into seclusion.
Not that she actually did.
If you have עדים *eidim* she committed adultery, who needs the process?
Even if you have עד אחד ed echad *ed echad* she committed
adultery, who needs the process? Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says...
מאי טעמא
*mai ta'ama*, what's the reason? אמר קרא *amar kra*, ונסתרה והיא נטמאה
ועד אין בה *venistarah vehi nitma'ah ve'eid ein bah*, she went into
seclusion and she became נטמאה *nitma'ah* and there is no witness. דליכא
דידע בה *deleka deyadah bah* means that nobody knows about it. לאפוקי
הא
דאיכא דידע בה *le'apukei ha de'ika deyadah bah* to exclude this case
where somebody knows about it, then end of story. So the interesting
question is how... are these עדים *eidim* or what if it's an
עד אחד ed echad *ed echad*? Because we actually learned that an
עד אחד ed echad *ed echad*, right, is believed after קינוי kinuy
*kinui* and סתירה *stirah*. So would the water not work if there
was an עד אחד somewhere? So תוספות Tosafot isn't so sure. Okay,
and the question also, as we're going to get to the גמרא,
Gemara is what happens if the witnesses come after the water—you did
the ritual and now the witnesses show up and now it was
like according to him now, oh now we understand why the ritual
didn't work because actually you know and so on. What if only
one witness showed up after the ritual? When do we say the
עד אחד is believed after קינוי וסתירה? kinui ve-setirah? Is it only
prior to the ritual to prevent us from going through the ritual
and whatever? Or do we say, no, even after that ritual was
done, when an עד אחד shows up, that becomes enough of a,
you know, basis to override, you know, sort of whatever the ritual
seemed to have demonstrated.
She still goes to her husband
then, is that what you're saying? Yeah. So anyway, but, but that
is a question, whether specifically we mean עדים or even עד אחד
in this idea that it would impact whether the water would work.
Okay, and I jumped a little bit ahead, but now we're also
going to see what happens when they show up after the ritual.
Okay, so that's what he says. ואנהר להו עינין ממתניתין ve-anharei lehu
einin mi-matnitin and he enlightened us—gave light to our eyes from the
משנה. Mishnah דקתני, de-katani, enlightened us. ודקתני ve-de-katani which ושבאו לה עדים
שהיא טמאה ve-shabba'u lah edim she-hi teme'ah and witnesses came that she
was טמאה. teme'a. And in that case, she would not drink. דאתו
עדים אימת? de-attu edim eimat? Now, when are the witnesses coming that
now she's forbidden, you know, and that she doesn't drink and that
she's forbidden to תרומה? terumah. אי נימא מקמי דתשתי, ei neima mi-kammei
de-tishtei, if it's before she drank, זונה היא. zonah hi. Of course,
now she's a, you know, a demonstrated, like, you know, a proven
adulteress. So of course the משנה Mishnah, doesn't have to say the
woman's proven to have committed adultery doesn't eat תרומה. Why, what's the
חידוש? אלא לבתר דשתי, ela le-vatar de-shatei, the משנה Mishnah. must mean
that after she drinks the water and it seems like she came
out clean, even so the witnesses showed, even after that the witnesses
showed up.
אי אמרת בשלמא אין המים בודקין אותה שפיר, ei amart bishlama ein
ha-mayim bodkin otah shapir,
if the water does not check her, given that if there were
witnesses, now we know why we would believe the witnesses, because now
that there are witnesses, we understand that even though the ritual looked
like she was innocent, it really, there's a different explanation why the
ritual didn't work. Okay, so now then we believe the witnesses. אלא
אי אמרת מים בודקין אותה, ela ei amart mayim bodkin otah, but
if the water works even when there are witnesses elsewhere, so תגלי
מילתא למפרע דסהדי שקרי נינהו. tiggallei milta le-mafrea de-sahadei shikrei ninhu. Now
it should become retroactively clear that these witnesses are lying, right? Because
if we assume that the ritual always works, so then the witnesses
showed up, well, the ritual proved her innocent, so what you're saying,
you must be lying. Now I love, I love this because here
you take something which is like, you know, for us this is
always like, you know, trial by ordeal, trial by miracle, right? And
we, but once we've put it all within a type of a
בית דין Beit Din, context, which is what this whole מסכת Masechet
does, it puts this whole ritual under objective evidence, witnesses, בית דין,
all these types of things. So now the ritual becomes good evidence,
you know, in a court and would actually trump the testimony of
witnesses. How could we trust these witnesses? The ritual is stronger evidence,
right?
But didn't we also say, don't we also have this principle of
כל זמן שהאיש מנוקה מעון? kol zeman she-ha-ish menukkeh me-avon?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara... is going to get to that. Maybe
there are other explanations. Fine. Anyway, so it says like, so the
fact that, so the fact that presumably we trust the witnesses after
shows that that must be because now we understand that because there
were witnesses, the water didn't work. So that proves his point. Okay.
אמר
ליה רב יוסף, amar leh Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said back, לעולם אימא לך מים בודקין אותה. le-olam eima lach mayim
bodkin otah. I will tell you that the water will work even
if there are witnesses. והא אימור זכות תולה לה. ve-ha eimur zekhut
tolah lah. So that Michael said, there's other explanations why the water
didn't work. How can we trust the witnesses then? Why doesn't the
ritual, the water, prove she was innocent? No, there were maybe other
reasons why it didn't work. For example, if she had merit then
it would not be immediately effective. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
במאי קמיפלגי, be-mai kammi-palgi, what are they debating? במינוולא דרבי, be-minvella de-Rabbi,
with Rabbi's statement that she would sort of get sicker and sicker
if even if the merit is sort of postponing it. Yeah, but
I don't know exactly the root, deteriorate, that was what I was
looking for, thank you. The question of deterioration. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught
in the משנה, Mishnah. רבי אומר זכות תולה במים המרים, Rabbi omer
zekhut tolah ba-mayim ha-marim, that if she has merit, it sort of
suspends the effect of the water. ואינה יולדת ואינה משבחת, ve-einah yoledet
ve-einah meshabbechat, so it doesn't have the positive effect, obviously if she's
guilty, she doesn't give birth, but it doesn't have the negative, but
and she doesn't get better, you know, it doesn't make her, like,
it doesn't have any of the positive effect. אלא מינוולא והולכת, ela
minvella ve-holechet, she deteriorates, she continues to deteriorate. לסוף היא מתה באותה
מיתה. le-sof hi metah be-otah mitah. In the end, she has the
death that the תורה described. Delayed reaction. Right, and it's like over
a period of time and maybe not as obvious. Right, maybe. באותה
מיתה. be-otah mitah. רב ששת Rav Sheshes, סבר בין לרבי *Rav Sheshet
savar bein le'Rabbi* now what do the Rabbis hold? That's what Rabbi
holds. So what do the Rabbis hold? So the Rabbis we assume
also agree that the זכות zechut *zechut* prevents her from dying right
away. But do they also agree with Rabbi that there's slow and
immediately obvious deterioration or do they say it's, you know, there's no
obvious, it just postpones it and then it happens at some very
distant time? So רב ששת סבר בין לרבי בין לרבנן היא hee,
משתבנא *Rav Sheshet savar bein le'Rabbi bein le'Rabbanan hi misnavna* that whether
according to Rabbi or the רבנן *Rabbanan* she will deteriorate. So therefore,
basically, the Rabbis don't disagree with Rabbi. Okay, so therefore in that,
if that's true... Oh no, I think the question is maybe the
Rabbis say that she doesn't die. Hold on, I think I got
that wrong. One minute.
Oh yeah, I'm sorry, I got it wrong. According to the Rabbis,
the Rabbis disagree with Rabbi and say she does not die. The
זכות *zechut* is תולה tola. *tola* and she doesn't die at all.
Okay, so Rabbi is responding. The Rabbis said the זכות *zechut* is
תולה *tola* and she doesn't die. And Rabbi said it's not true,
she deteriorates and dies. So the question is, do the Rabbis say
that even though she doesn't die, do they say that she deteriorates?
Okay, that's the question. So if everybody agrees that she deteriorates and
they only debate if she dies, right, then the point is, well,
if she came out totally clean, then you can't say that it
was because of זכות תולה לה *zechut tola la* because according to
everybody you would have seen her deteriorate. So that should have been
a complete evidence that she was innocent. And now the witnesses say
she's guilty, we should be throwing out the witnesses. The only way
she could be totally not, the water could be totally not effective
is either the witnesses are lying, or because the witnesses, if there
are witnesses, the water isn't effective. Okay, so that's what רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet* says. One minute. Hold on, hold on. So it says
like this. So רב ששת סבר *Rav
Sheshet
savar*, now I totally lost my place, רב ששת סבר בין לרבי
בין לרבנן היא משתבנא *Rav Sheshet savar bein le'Rabbi bein le'Rabbanan hi
misnavna* that either way she deteriorates. And therefore, if the water had
no effect, so our conclusion is either she's innocent and the witnesses
are lying, or that the water doesn't work when there are witnesses.
And since the משנה *Mishna* makes it clear we believe the witnesses,
that proves that the water doesn't work when there are witnesses. לרב
יוסף סבר *le'Rav Yosef savar*, רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* says,
לרבי היא משתבנא *le'Rabbi hi misnavna* for Rabbi she deteriorates, לרבנן לא
הויא משתבנא *le'Rabbanan la havya misnavna* for the רבנן *Rabbanan* she wouldn't
deteriorate. And she wouldn't die either? And she wouldn't die either, there
would be no obvious effect of the water. And therefore, that's why
we believe the witnesses, not because the witnesses prevent the water from
working, but because there could be other causes that the water didn't
work because
of because because of her merit, okay? You had a question. I
did.
Yes. So according to the position of רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* that
if there are witnesses somewhere, somewhere
in
the world, we don't know where, right, but they saw actually the
adultery, yeah, then the waters won't work. Yeah. So anytime a woman
drinks these waters, goes through the ritual, and it doesn't work, right,
there would still be a suspended suspicion?
Right, that's what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is about to get to.
Or of course she has some זכות *zechut*.
Right,
but
also according to the רבנן *Rabbanan* after three years she just dies.
She won't waste away, but she will...
No, no, I said it wrong. I said the רבנן *Rabbanan* actually
say she doesn't die. The זכות *zechut* is so good that it's
תולה *tola* and she doesn't die.
Oh, I thought she just didn't deteriorate.
No, so I correct myself. I said that according to Rabbi she
deteriorates and dies. The רבנן *Rabbanan* say she doesn't die and the
question is do they think that she even deteriorates? According to one
opinion, according to the רבנן *Rabbanan* there's no marked, no effect of
the water if she has זכות *zechut*. Which always then raises the
question that why doesn't that just undermine the entire process? Which is
what the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is about to ask. So let's take
a look at the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so basically where we
are right now is that the witnesses come, we're assuming the case
in the משנה *Mishna* is witnesses came after the water and we
believe the witnesses. So the question is, why do we believe the
witnesses? Why doesn't the water ritual like prove them lying? So right
now we have two explanations: either because it proves the point that
if there are witnesses, the water doesn't work, or because there's other
reasons the water didn't work. It would be like the position of
the חכמים *chachamim* who argue on Rabbi, who would say that if
she has זכות *zechut*, it would be no effect of the water.
We completely neutralize the effect. So there's two different ways of understanding
why the water didn't trump the witnesses. And one of them is
evidence that would be the position that if there are witnesses, the
water is ineffective, but there's another way of reading it, that it
was ineffective for a different reason, it was ineffective because she had
זכות *zechut* and according to the Rabbis who argue on Rabbi, it
had absolutely no effect when she has זכות *zechut*. Okay?
There's a note here attributed to רש״י Rashi. *Rashi* which seems to...
Yes, says what?
According to רב יוסף Rav Yosef? *Rav Yosef*, the Rabbis altogether dispute
Rabbi's assertion that the סוטה *Sotah* for merit suspends punishment gradually wasting
away, rather if she shows no immediate ill effects from the bitter
waters, when the extension granted her by her merit ends, she dies
suddenly.
Oh, so she does die in the end.
According to רש״י *Rashi*.
This רש״י *Rashi* according...
And the זכות *zechut* is...
Oh, this רש״י *Rashi* that I read said one minute, hold on.
I don't see that in the רש״י רב ששת סבר. Rashi Rav
Sheshet savar The way I read רש״י רב ששת סבר is that
the rabbis say that she doesn't die. But okay.
Anyway, it says according to רב יוסף Rav Yosef? is the רש״י.
Oh, according to רב יוסף?
Yeah, the rabbis on 20a it says we altogether dispute.
Oh, according to רב יוסף? Okay fine, which I was talking about
רב ששת. All right, let's move on. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. רב ששת said wait,
אמר רבי אמר רבנן. amar Rabbi amar rabbanan. Okay.
Okay, fine. Okay. מתיב רבי שמעון בר אשי. metiv Rabbi Shimon bar
Ashi. רבי שמעון בר אשי Rabbi Shimon bar Ashi asks, רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, אין זכות תולה במים המארים. ein zechut tola
bemayim hamarim. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, I can't buy into any
of this thing about the זכות being תולה. ואם אתה אומר זכות
תולה במים המארים, ve'im ata omer zechut tola bemayim hamarim, because if
you were to say such a thing, מדחה אתה את המים בפני
כל הנשים השוטות, madche ata et hamayim bifnei kol hanashim hashotot,
you basically are undermining the effect of the water for all women
that have to undergo this ritual, now everybody will basically say, you
know, this is bogus, I know so and so who did commit
adultery and the water didn't work for her, and you basically, you
know, undermine its power for all those women. ואתה מוציא שם רע
על הטהורות ששתו, ve'ata motzi shem ra al hatehorot sheshatu, and then
you also are libeling all the women that were legitimately innocent, כי
הם אומרים טמאות היו אלא שתלה להם זכות, ki heim omrim temei'ot
hayu ela shetala lahem zechut, because they'll say they were actually all
guilty. So the women who are guilty will say you can get
away with it, and the women who are innocent people will suspect
them of being guilty. The whole thing is undermined. So you can't
come up with, you can't say this idea. ואם איתא, ve'im ita,
now of course what's so fascinating about this is is that like,
here we're trying to figure out whether miraculously it had this effect
or not, and we're determining it based on whether like logically it
could have worked out, you know, sort of like, well according to
way I understand what good policy would have been, this could not
have, this cannot be true. So obviously it wasn't true.
Okay, so anyway, ואם איתא,
ve'im ita, if it's true, יש עדים במדינת הים נמי אתה מוציא
שם רע על הטהורות ששתו ואין אומרים טמאות היו
אלא שיש עדים במדינת הים.
yesh eidim bimdinat hayam nami ata motzi shem ra al hatehorot sheshatu
ve'ein
omrim temei'ot hayu ela sheyesh eidim bimdinat hayam.
So according to that, רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon critique should be just
as good, just as legitimate on this idea that if witnesses far
away, you know, prevent the water, that's going to make every woman
who comes out innocent suspect, people will suspect, maybe she's really guilty
and there's witnesses somewhere.
But I thought we said he didn't say that or?
So how do you answer that critique? So the גמרא says, רבי
שמעון קאמרת? Rabbi Shimon kaamart? You want to know about רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? Of course רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon wouldn't agree with me.
רבי שמעון מידי דזכות לא תלי עדים נמי לא תלו. Rabbi Shimon
midei dezechut lo tali eidim nami lo talu. Of course רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon rejects any of the idea that anything else could interfere
with the process. Okay. But I'm saying within the idea that if
we accept that other things interfere with the process, so עדים could
also interfere with the process. Okay. מתיב רב. metiv Rav. So רב
asked, ואלו שמנחותיהם נשרפות. ve'eilu sheminchoteihem nisrafot. The following women, their מנחות
minchot are burnt.
Okay, which means that even after they brought their מנחה mincha and
put it in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, right in the, in
the vessel which sanctified it, and once it's put in the כלי
שרת kli sharet you cannot be פודה podeh it, you can't redeem
it. So if they brought all you can do with it is
burn it. But even so, if the process gets interrupted in the
middle, and you can't bring the מנחה, mincha, then you can't redeem
it, so at that stage all you can do is burn it.
So who falls in that category? All, pretty much everybody like in
our משנה. האומרת טמאה teme'a, אני, a woman who admits she's guilty,
we would stop the process and burn the מנחה. mincha. ושבאו לה
עדים שהיא טמאה, ushebau la eidim shehi temei'a, and that witnesses came,
just like our משנה. So back to the same question. דאתו עדים
אימת? de'atu eidim eimat? Now this is before she drinks the water,
okay. So when do the witnesses come? אילימא מקמי דתתקדש, eileima mikamei
detitkadesh, if it's before you put the מנחה mincha in the vessel,
תפרוק ותיחולין, tifrok veteichulin, just redeem it.
אלא לבתר דתתקדש, ela levatar detitkadesh, it was put in the vessel.
Okay, and then it was put in the vessel, now it's, so
it's קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, we can't redeem it, we can't continue
the process, we have to burn it. אי אמרת בשלמא מים בודקין
אותה, ei amart bishlama mayim bodkin ota, if, had the witnesses not
come, the waters would have done their job, אלמא בת הקרבה היא,
alma bat hakrava hi, then we would, then it would have been
fine, it's something that could have been brought, had the witnesses not
come it would have been a completely fine process and it would
have worked.
וכי קדוש מעיקרא שפיר קדוש, vechi kadosh mei'ikara shapir kadosh, and when
it was sanctified, it was properly sanctified because it was a process
that could have been completed.
ומשום הכי מנחתה נשרפת, umishum hachi minchata nisrefet, and therefore we burn
it. אלא אי אמרת אין המים בודקין אותה, ela ei amart ein
hamayim bodkin ota, but if, now that we know there are witnesses,
what do we realize? We realize that the whole process never would
have worked, right? The witnesses showed
up. So now
that we realize this, טיבי ומבטלא למפרע, tibi u-mevatla le-mafrea, we retroactively
realize דקדוש מעיקרא בטעות קדוש de-kadosh me-ikara be-ta'ut kadosh that the whole
thing was an error because the whole process wasn't fit for working
from the get-go, even had they not shown up, it would not
have been an effective process, right? So now the whole sanctity was
בטעות be-ta'ut and ותיפוק לחולין ve-tipok le-chulin and now we shouldn't even
have to redeem it, everything was בטעות, be-ta'ut, we wouldn't have to
burn the מנחה, mincha, it wasn't קדוש kadosh and because the whole
thing was being done בטעות be-ta'ut it would have been an ineffective
process, an ineffectual process, even in the כלי שרת. kli sharet. Right.
So the גמרא... ותיפוק לחולין! ve-tipok le-chulin! So that's a good question.
אמר רב יהודה מדסקרתא, Amar Rav Yehuda mi-Diskarta, כגון שזינתה בעזרה. kegon
she-zinta ba-azara. Okay. So what happened was no, no, no, no, it
was ready to work because there weren't witnesses about something she did
a year ago and the witnesses were in Spain and they just
showed up. The witnesses came and said to us after you put
the מנחה mincha in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, she went ahead
and we saw her sneak off into some room and commit adultery
in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
And that's why we can't go through with it. But when you
put it in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, it actually attached status,
you know, there were no witnesses whether she was innocent or guilty,
we don't know, but there were no witnesses and it was fit
for working, the process. It only becomes unfit once that now of
course the funny thing is but that's not what she was suspected
of, she was suspected of adultery, unless you're saying it's the same
guy. But anyway, but one of the things we do wind up
saying is that she says ואמרה האשה אמן אמן, ve-amra ha-isha amen
amen, so we say אמן מאיש זה אמן מאיש אחר. amen me-ish
zeh amen me-ish acher. So once she's going through this process, even
if the actual commit of adultery she committed adultery with a different
man, she also the waters have the same effect. So that's so
interesting what you're saying, that if there were witnesses of a committing
adultery, even not the one that she was specifically suspected of, nevertheless,
like the waters presumably would find her guilty and the presence of
the witnesses prevents the waters from working. Yes.
Isn't this a comparable case with הקדש? hekdesh? Aren't we very strict
about things that weren't really קדוש kadosh but they...
Oh, so we're going to get to that answer, that maybe we're
just... okay, so we'll get to that answer. So let's take a
look. But let's have some fun here. So it
says כגון שזינתה בעזרה, kegon she-zinta ba-azara, דקדוש מעיקרא שפיר קדוש. de-kadosh
me-ikara shapir kadosh. And the witnesses were just about this one act
she did right now, and that's enough to interrupt the process. So
מתיב רב משארשיא, metiv Rav Mesharshiya, ולו פירחי כהונה מלווין אותה. ve-lo
pirchei kehuna melavin ota. What do you mean? She's got an escort!
How does she commit adultery?
Maybe... so what about the כהן kohen that's accompanying her? So the
גמרא says שזינתה מפרחי כהונה! she-zinta mi-pirchei kehuna! All right! So she
had it with one of them! So poor thing. רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, כגון שנצרכה לנקביה.
kegon she-nitzrecha li-nekaveha. No, she had to go to the bathroom. אטו
פירחי כהונה בבית הכסא נמי עללו לה? atu pirchei kehuna be-veit ha-kisei
nami alalu lah? What, you think they keep her like in a,
you know, in a jail? So, you know, they give her some
freedom of movement, so she had excuse me, I've got to go
to the bathroom, and that's when she did it. Okay. Anyway, that
was one answer. That was fun. רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar,
now רב פפא Rav Papa says לעולם כדאמרינן מעיקרא.
le-olam ke-da-amrinan me-ikara.
It's like we always said. דקאמרת תיפוק לחולין. de-ka-amrat tipok le-chulin. What
do you mean...
meaning not that she committed adultery, not that she committed adultery in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay. The witnesses came and said she
committed adultery a year ago, okay, and they were in Spain and
they just got here now. So now why don't we say retroactively
it was not sanctified because it was all בטעות, be-ta'ut, because it
never would have worked? So it says מדרבנן גזירה שמא יאמרו מוציאין
מכלי שרת לחול, mi-de-rabbanan gezeira shema yomru motzi'in mi-kli sharet le-chol,
which I think is effectively right what you asked, which is: Yeah,
okay, you're right, technically it's not קדוש kadosh and you could just
go ahead and eat this מנחה mincha whatever, it never was sanctified,
but it looks to everybody like it was sanctified, and people don't
know this הלכה halacha that because of the עדים retroactively it never
would have been effective or whatever. So therefore because of that, that
people should not suspect like how are we taking something that was
sanctified in a כלי שרת kli sharet and not treating it with
קדושה? kedusha? Therefore we burn it. Okay, so רמי בר רב מרי,
Rami bar Rav Mari, so רמי בר רב מרי Rami bar Rav
Mari asks, so good, you see when you stop talking,
so that means you're too engaged. All right, so רמי בר רב
מרי, Rami bar Rav Mari, so רמי בר רב מרי Rami bar
Rav Mari asks, נטמאת מנחתה עד שלא קידשה בכלי, nitme'a minchata ad
she-lo kidsha ba-kli, הרי היא ככל המנחות ותיפדה. harei hi ke-chol ha-menachot
ve-tipade. So there's a... so here the סוטה's מנחה, mincha, not that
the process is not going to be good because she admitted or
witnesses came or whatever, it's just a normal thing happened. The מנחה
mincha became טמאה. So if it was before it was put in
the כלי שרת, kli sharet, so הרי היא ככל המנחות ותיפדה, harei
hi ke-chol ha-menachot ve-tipade, so it's like all מנחות menachot before it
was put in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, it could be redeemed.
It doesn't have קדושת הגוף. kedushat ha-guf. You just redeem its value
and you use the money on whatever or you bring another מנחה.
mincha. משקידשה בכלי, mi-she-kidsha ba-kli,
once it was put in the כלי שרת kli sharet and it
became טמאה, then it's קדושת הגוף, kedushat ha-guf, you can't do anything,
הרי היא ככל המנחות ותישרף, harei hi ke-chol ha-menachot ve-tisaref, it gets
burned. Now, קידש הקומץ, kidesh ha-kometz, you took the handbreadth from it,
ולא הספיק להקריבו, ve-lo hispik le-hakrivo, and you didn't yet offer it
up on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, עד שמת הוא או עד שמתה היא.
ad she-met hu o ad she-meta hi.
Now here he or she died. So now it's a more normal
particularly סוטה-ry reason you can't go through with it. Nobody admit... But
if one of the relevant parties dies, you’re not going to go
through the process, okay? So what do you do? You can’t, it’s
sanctified קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, you can’t redeem it, you can’t go
through with the process because there’s no longer a point because they’re
dead. So in that case הרי ככל המנחות ותישרף, harei k’chol haminchos
v’tisareif, so then you have to burn it, nothing left to do.
קרב הקומץ, kareiv hakometz, it was offered up, ולא הספיקו לאכול שיירים,
v’lo hispiku le’echol sheyaryim, עד שמתו ad shemeisu או עד שמתה היא.
o ad shemeisa hee. And now it was burnt and the מנחה
mincha was a כשר kosher קרבן. korban. And now just now there’s
no,
we’re not going to continue the ritual with the water because one
of the parties is dead. But as a קרבן, korban, when it
was brought, it was everything was in place, it was brought with
all the proper, you know, requirements were met, and it was still
a process at that stage seemed like it was going to continue.
So in that case הרי ככל המנחות ותאכל, harei k’chol haminchos v’tei’achel,
so then you go out and eat it. It was brought legitimately.
של ספק באה מתחילה, shel safeik ba’ah mitchila, at the very outset
it was brought out of doubt, okay? וכפרה ספיקה והלכה לה, v’kippara
s’fika v’halcha la,
it, it now, the way כפרה kippara Rashi says, does not mean
atone, but it sort of meant it did its job, it worked,
it was brought as it was supposed to have been brought, okay?
The fact that like retroactively we didn’t need to clarify because one
of them were going to die, who cares at the time? We
didn’t know. And at the time we didn’t know whether she was
innocent or guilty. There was always an element of like what purpose
it was going to serve. Okay, but it was done in the
right context, so we’re done. באו עדים, bau eidim, that, okay, that’s
all background, not relevant for our point. באו עדים שהיא טמאה, bau
eidim she’hee temei’ah,
now finally the witnesses are coming, מנחתה תישרף, minchasah tisareif, okay,
they’re burnt. Now again, that’s either because retroactively, either because
now you can’t do it, or the other explanation would be retroactively
we see it never could have been done. Really it never should
have been קדוש, kadosh, but now the argument would be because of
מדרבנן. miderabbanan.
We don’t want it to look like we’re just de-sanctifying something that
was sanctified. Okay.
תישרף tisareif means אגבי המזבח? agavei hamizbei’ach?
No, no, no, בית הדשן, beis hadeshen, right, not as a... נמצאו
עדי זוממין, nimtzu eidei zomemin, now what happens if the witnesses of
the קינוי and the סתירה, which allowed us to go through the
process, were lying? They were proven to have falsified their testimony, okay,
by another pair of witnesses. Yeah. In that case, מנחתה חולין, minchasah
chulin, מנחתה חולין. minchasah chulin. In that case, ah,
so the whole thing was a bogus to begin with, so we
can go ahead and just eat the מנחה. mincha. It’s חולין, chulin,
it was never sanctified. You don’t have to burn it, you don’t
have to redeem it, it was never sanctified. So the question is,
right? So you just got through saying that even if retroactively it
was not valid, we would have to burn it because of appearances.
Well here retroactively was not valid, right, because the whole basis, the
whole initial witnesses were lying, and we say we don’t have to
burn it, we say we can treat it as חולין. chulin. So
how do you reconcile that?
And she goes home with her husband?
And she goes home with her husband, yeah. So the גמרא says,
עדים זוממין קאמרת? eidim zomemin ka’amaras? One minute, you’re talking about witnesses
that have been proven to, to perjure themselves? עדים זוממין קלא אית
להו. eidim zomemin kala is lehu. No, everybody finds out about that.
Like oh my god, did you hear that the witnesses were lying
or whatever? And other witnesses have to come to prove those witnesses
lying. So everybody realizes, and also like it becomes clear that the
whole story was a, was bogus, right? When it’s clear that, I
mean it’s not just I think that people find out about the
עדים זוממין, eidim zomemin, it becomes obvious that there was no basis
for it and you understand why the מנחה mincha wasn’t sanctified. But
when witnesses come at the end to say she committed adultery, you
don’t understand why the whole process was bogus. Who knows that הלכה
halacha that all, that you know, the waters won’t work in those
cases? Okay. So the גמרא says, תני כוותיה דרב ששת, tani k’vassa
d’Rav Sheshes, it’s taught like רב ששת, ולאו מטעמיה, v’lav mita’amei, but
not, but not based on the same פסוק pasuk he gets it
from, because he got it from עדים בה, eidim bah, and here’s
where, where we get it from. וטהורה, v’tehora, וטהורה. v’tehora.
It says וטהורה היא, v’tehora hee, ונקתה ונזרעה זרע, v’niksa v’nizre’ah zara,
right, then when it works and she is pure. וטהורה, v’tehora, ולא
שיש לה עדים במדינת הים. v’lo she’yesh lah eidim b’medinas hayam. The
waters will only prove that she’s וטהורה, v’tehora, will work if she’s
really וטהורה. v’tehora. But if there’s, but if there’s witnesses במדינת הים,
b’medinas hayam, then maybe she came out clean for a different reason,
the waters are not going to work in that case. Okay, so
that’s where it learns it from, same הלכה halacha from a different
פסוק. pasuk. וטהורה, v’tehora, the extra וי"ו, vav, ולא שתולה לה זכות,
v’lo she’tola lah zechus,
and not that there’s another, some other reason, right, that she has
some merit. היא, ולא שישאו ויתנו בה מוזרות בלבנה. v’lo she’yisu v’yitnu
bah mozeros b’levana. So
now this is an interesting point. If everybody is, she is so
guilty that everybody is, or so suspected, perceived that everybody is gossiping
about her. It says, it talks about the women knitting in the
moonlight. Okay, so if all the יענטעס yentas are gossiping about her,
the waters don’t work. So, okay, so which is a very interesting
דרשה. drasha. Okay, so that, so anyway, but we learn out that
there are other reasons why the waters don’t, other things the waters
don’t work and one of them is that there were witnesses במדינת
הים. b’medinas hayam. And now the גמרא says, ורבי שמעון נהי דווי"ו
לא דריש, v’Rabbi Shimon nehi d’vav lo darish, Rabbi Shimon who rejects
these explanations says that nothing will prevent the waters from working because
then it undermines the whole, you know, efficacy or of the waters
or the whole like legitimacy of the waters. But he could still,
the
word טהורה tehora should still teach,
he should still concede that that teaches the idea that if there
are עדים במדינת הים edim b'medinas hayam the waters shouldn't work. What
is that word טהורה tehora doing? Why can't he concede that point?
So the גמרא says, you know what? לא שכיחא, lo shchicha, that's
not common. So maybe there are some rare cases where there'll be
another explanation why the waters doesn't work, but as opposed to what
we said before, which is that רבי שמעון Reb Shimon would, which
actually was a more satisfying answer, I think, that רבי שמעון Reb
Shimon would reject any other explanation because then it undermines the waters.
Here we're saying because of the דרשה drasha from the פסוק, pasuk,
he can't really deny the דרשה drasha that he'd have to concede
that the case of עדים במדינת הים would impact the waters, but
that's not going to affect their legitimacy because it's such a rare
case that's not going to have a bigger impact in terms of
the perceived legitimacy of the waters.